<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <!-- The below took me about 1.5 hours (from OxGarage output to usable TEI that could be the basis for a simple HTML). There is much more that could (must?) be done. On the markup side especially:
        Marking all names and referencing them to, say, wikidata.
        Linking the references in text and notes to their respective items in the bibl.
        If all places are identified in wikidata, GeoNames or another palcename gazetteer, it should be possible to produce maps on the fly from there. See the beginning of <listPlace> in the <back>-->
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Strangers in Paradise – Foreigners on Mount Putuo in the Late Qing</title>
        <author>Marcus Bingenheimer</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>Asia-Pacific Island and Littoral Studies Vol. 0 (2019)</edition>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <persName>Oliver Streiter</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editor</resp>
          <persName>Marcus Bingenheimer</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Chief Technology Officer</resp>
          <persName>Simon Wiles</persName>
        </respStmt>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Editorial Assistant</resp>
          <persName>Manwai Toh</persName>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <ab>
          Received:<date>2019-07-31</date>.
          Finished review: <date>2019-07-31</date>.
          Published online: <date>2019-??</date>.
        </ab>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <ab>Submitted by the author via email as ODT file with images.</ab>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <xenoData>
      <!-- BibTex and/or DC  goes here-->
    </xenoData>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <docTitle>
        <titlePart>Strangers in Paradise – Foreigners on Mount Putuo in the Late Qing<note xml:id="ftn1" place="foot" n="1">
            <p>I am grateful to Professor Katsufumi
              Narita and the Graduate School of International Development at Nagoya
              University, for hosting me as Visiting Research Fellow in Fall 2015,
              where much of the research for this paper took place. Thanks are also
              due to Jinhua Chen, Timothy Barrett and Anne Baycroft, who all provided
              new and interesting information.</p>
            <p> In all quotations I have
              regularized “Ningbo”, “Putuo” and some other names to their pinyin
              spelling.</p>
          </note>
        </titlePart>
      </docTitle>
      <docAuthor>Marcus Bingenheimer</docAuthor>
      <docDate>2019</docDate>
      <docEdition>
        <!-- from  /TEI/teiHeader[1]/fileDesc[1]/editionStmt[1]/edition[1]-->
      </docEdition>
      <div type="abstract">
        <p>Mount Putuo is a small island in the Zhoushan archipelago near Ningbo, located
          some four kilometer east of the main island Zhoushan. For more than a thousand
          years Chinese Buddhists have considered Mount Putuo to be the abode of the
          Bodhisattva Guanyin and the island was and is one of the most popular pilgrimage
          sites in China. Its many visitors have left numerous notes, poems and
          travelogues that describe the island from the 12th to the 18th century. These
          texts are collected in a series of so-called temple or mountain gazetteers (<hi rend="italic">sizhi</hi> 寺志/ <hi rend="italic">shanzhi</hi> 山志). For the
          last decades of the Qing Dynasty (1644-1911), however, there is a lack of
          Chinese accounts. Not quite coincidentally, as this article will argue, it is
          around this time that foreigners start to visit Mount Putuo. The island is
          mentioned in numerous accounts by European and American travelers such as C.
          Gützlaff, W. Medhurst, R. Fortune, N. Rondot, É. Huc, A. Little, T. Watters, B.
          Laufer, and C. Kupfer. Those visitors often left descriptions that reveal a
          wealth of detail about life on the island at a time for which few Chinese
          records exist. Below we will discuss the reasons behind this constellation of
          sources and summarize the descriptions by foreign visitors to Mount Putuo in
          order to complement the record of the Putuo gazetteers.</p>
      </div>
      <div type="keywords">
        <list xml:lang="en">
          <item>Mount Putuo</item>
          <item>19th century Missionaries in China</item>
        </list>
        <list xml:lang="zh">
          <item>普陀山</item>
          <item>19世紀傳教士在中國</item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </front>

    <body>
      <div type="articleBody">
        <div type="section">

          <head>Introduction</head>
          <p>For Chinese Buddhists the island of Mount Putuo 普陀山 near Ningbo 寧波 is the abode
            of Guanyin 觀音 (Skt. Avalokiteśvara), the Bodhisattva of Compassion. At least
            since the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century believers went to the island site to
            pray and perhaps glimpse the Bodhisattva herself, who was thought to dwell in
            one of the steep grottoes along the picturesque shoreline. Over the centuries
            the site’s fortunes varied. Patronized by the imperial court during the Song and
            Yuan the island attracted increasing numbers of pilgrims. This changed during
            the early and mid Ming when Mount Putuo was closed to pilgrimage travel for
            almost hundred fifty years as part of various ocean embargoes (<hi rend="italic">haijin </hi> 海禁). It was only in the mid 16<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century
            that the site was reopened in the wake of a general revival of Buddhism in the
            late Ming especially in the Jiangnan region. In the late Ming and early Qing
            both imperial court and local gentry supported the temples on the island and
            there is evidence for a lively pilgrimage scene that encouraged the expansion of
            monastic and other settlements into the north of the island. The Kangxi (r.
            1661-1722) and Yongzheng (r. 1722-1735) emperors bestowed gifts on Mount Putuo
            and the monastic leadership was well connected at court. During the reign of the
            Qianlong emperor (r. 1735-1796), who favored Tibetan, not Chinese Buddhism,
            imperial patronage decreased, but Mount Putuo remained a popular pilgrimage
            site.</p>
          <p>As we will see below, in the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century pilgrimage to the
            site again declined when the Opium Wars (1839–1842 and 1856–1860) and the
            Taiping Civil War (1850–1864) made pilgrimage travel difficult.<note xml:id="ftn2" place="foot" n="2">For the term “civil war” instead of
              “rebellion” see Meyer-Fong (2013: 11).</note> Mount Putuo was, at least in
            part, economically reliant on a steady flow of visitors for the upkeep of its
            infrastructure. The temples also owned land on neighboring islands, especially
            Zhoushan and Zhujiajian 朱家尖, that was rented out to tenants.<note xml:id="ftn3" place="foot" n="3">Butler (1879: 122).</note> As such they might have been
            directly affected by the British invasion and occupation of Dinghai (1840-46),
            the main harbor of Zhoushan. Especially the Taiping civil war, in which by some
            estimates more people perished than in the first World War, would have impacted
            leisure travel in the East China Sea.<note xml:id="ftn4" place="foot" n="4">For
              a more extensive overview of the history of Mount Putuo see Bingenheimer
              (2016: 16-28).</note> Although neither Zhoushan nor Mount Putuo saw active
            fighting in the Taiping campaigns, due to the combined pressures of foreign
            presence on the coast and the civil war in the interior the Qing lost control
            over the archipelago. As a consequence piracy impacted both merchant and
            pilgrimage travel around Zhoushan.<note xml:id="ftn5" place="foot" n="5">See
              Butler (1879: 120) and Martin (1897: 122-123) discussed below.</note> The
            reports by foreign travelers mention hundreds of monks and dozens of temples,
            but also often remark on the dilapidated state of the buildings – without,
            however, associating the difficult times with there own presence there.</p>
          <p>For most of its history visitors to Mount Putuo set out from Ningbo, entering
            Hangzhou Bay at Zhenhai and then following the south coast of Zhoushan Island
            often with a stopover at Dinghai. This route remained largely unchanged even
            after the introduction of steamships in the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century.
            For 1907/08 Boerschmann reports: </p>
          <p>[Mount Putuo] can be reached relatively easily. From Shanghai to Ningbo there are
            daily crossings, taking about twelve hours, on elegant and conveniently
            furnished steamships of French, English and also Chinese shipping lines. From
            the same pier in Ningpo, at which the large steamers arrive, smaller Chinese
            steamboats leave almost daily for the six to eight hour journey along the Ningbo
            River [...] via Dinghai the main city on Zhoushan […] with c.30,000 inhabitants,
            to its terminal at Shenjiamen [Island]. In summer, during pilgrim season, they
            even stop at Mount Putuo where they anchor near the coast, and one is taken to
            the island via small rowboats. Otherwise one takes a two to three hour trip on a
            sailing boat from Shenjiamen to Putuo.</p>
          <p>In summer the large steamships that ply the Shanghai Ningbo route sometimes make
            special trips to Mount Putuo that allow their passengers to stay at Mount Putuo
            for a whole day with enough time to visit the monasteries and take a bath at the
            marvelous beach on the east side of the island. The passengers are mostly
            European and thus the island is not unknown, it has been visited quite often,
            and described at times quite extensively.<note xml:id="ftn6" place="foot" n="6">Boerschmann (1911: 4-5). The Shanghai to Ningbo steamer route was running
              since the 1870s, without gaining speed. Some 30 years before Boerschmann,
              Hughes made the very same trip described by him, twelve hours from Shanghai
              to Ningbo, a one hour layover, and about six hours to Putuo (Hughes 1881:
              254-255).</note>
          </p>
          <p>These “at times quite extensive” descriptions form an important group of sources
            for our knowledge about this pilgrimage site, especially during the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">

          <head>Lack of Chinese sources vs. abundance of Western accounts</head>
          <p>Difficult times often leave their trace in the sources by an absence. The Putuo
            gazetteer of 1832 was not too well researched, but nevertheless offers some
            information about Mount Putuo under Qianlong (1735-1796) and Jiaqing
            (1796-1820). The next Putuo gazetteer was compiled in 1924, but lacks
            information about the mid 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, because Chinese
            sources for the mid 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century about Putuo were scarce.
            Consequently, the most recent Putuo gazetteer of 1999, although carefully
            researched, was not able to reconstruct even the exact succession of abbots of
            the main temples for the years between 1830 and 1875.<note xml:id="ftn7" place="foot" n="7">Wang Liansheng (1999: 509).</note> Another notable
            absence is the lack of miracle stories for this period.<note xml:id="ftn8" place="foot" n="8">Wang Liansheng (1999: 37).</note> Still another lacunae
            are travelogues. For the time before the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century the
            1999 Putuo gazetteer includes travelogues by the following authors:</p>
          <table>
            <row>
              <cell>Name</cell>
              <cell>Date of visit</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Xu Jing 徐兢</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1123</hi>-06-28
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Shi Hao 史浩</cell>
              <cell>between <hi rend="bold">1148</hi>-03-29/04-26</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Liu Geng 劉賡</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1298</hi>, 1299, and 1300
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Wu Lai 吳萊</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1324</hi>-06-30/07-29
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>[First Lacunae]</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Hou Jigao 侯繼高</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1588</hi>-03-30
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Tu Long 屠隆</cell>
              <cell>~1585-<hi rend="bold">1589</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Yin Yingyuan 尹應元</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1603</hi>-06-23
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Lu Bao 陸寶</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1617</hi>-03-20/27
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Zhu Guozhen 朱國禎</cell>
              <cell>early June <hi rend="bold">1617</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Zhang Dai 張岱</cell>
              <cell>late March, early April <hi rend="bold">1638</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Shi Shibiao 施世驃</cell>
              <cell>autumn- winter <hi rend="bold">1701</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Lao Zhibian 勞之辨</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1713</hi>-03-11/16
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>[Second Lacunae]</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Gao Henian 高鶴年</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1898</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p>While the 250 years that passed between the travel reports of Wu Lai and Hou
            Jigao are due to the forced closure of the site during the early and mid-Ming,
            the reasons for the gap between Lao Zhibian and Gao Henian are more difficult to
            ascertain.</p>
          <p>One explanation might be simply that there were indeed no new travelogues about
            Mount Putuo during much of the 18<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> centuries, although the travelogue genre enjoyed great popularity
            in that time.<note xml:id="ftn9" place="foot" n="9">Eggert (2004: 177).</note>
          </p>
          <p>Another explanation might be that editorial dynamics prevented the inclusion and
            production of travelogues on Mount Putuo. The editors of the 1832 gazetteer were
            not much concerned with updating the record of travelogues and have not added
            much beyond the earlier gazetteer (compiled in 1740). This, however, would
            explain only the absence of Chinese travelogues for the period until 1832, not
            for the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, as the 1924 gazetteer that should have
            listed these, was compiled with great care. Thus, if we lack Chinese travelogues
            for the period (in spite of an ever increasing output of travelogues overall),
            it is probably because fewer literati were interested in Mount Putuo and/or able
            to travel there.</p>
          <p>The dearth of Chinese travelogues for 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century Mount
            Putuo coincides, however, with a large number of reports by European and American
            travelers, missionaries, scholars, and adventurers, who described their sojourns
            to the sacred site. Among the most prominent were:<note xml:id="ftn10" place="foot" n="10">See the bibliography for their published works. There
              are a number of other, shorter accounts of voyages that were published in
              the newspapers of the French, German and English communities in China.
              Gützlaff’s is so far the first published account of a visit, but reports of
              earlier visits might still turn up in archives and letters.</note>
          </p>
          <table>
            <row>
              <cell>Name</cell>
              <cell>Date of visit</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Karl F. A. Gützlaff</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1833</hi>-02-04
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Walter Medhurst</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1835</hi>-10-19
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Robert Fortune </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1844</hi>-07
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Natalis Rondot</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1845</hi>-10-7/8
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Évariste R. Huc</cell>
              <cell> between <hi rend="bold">1840</hi>-53</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>John Nevius</cell>
              <cell> summers of <hi rend="bold">1854</hi>, <hi rend="bold">1855</hi>+<hi rend="bold">1856</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Helen Nevius</cell>
              <cell> summers of <hi rend="bold">1855</hi>+<hi rend="bold">1856</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>William A.P. Martin</cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1855</hi>
                <hi rend="bold">
                  <note xml:id="ftn11" place="foot" n="11">Martin visited at other times as
                    well. He arrived in Ningbo in 1850 <hi rend="italic">The Chinese
                      Repository</hi> Vol. 20 1851: 518, and lived there for six years
                    Martin 1897: 63. The year 1855 is mentioned in Martin 1897:
                    121.</note>
                </hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Michael S. Culbertson </cell>
              <cell>between <hi rend="bold">184</hi>
                <hi rend="bold">8</hi>
                <hi rend="bold">-5</hi>
                <hi rend="bold">6</hi>
                <note xml:id="ftn12" place="foot" n="12">Culbertson arrived in China 1844 and resided in Ningbo until 1851,
                  when he moved to Shanghai <hi rend="italic">Chinese Repository</hi> Vol. 20
                  1851: 516-17. The figure he gives for the number of monks on the island
                  c. 300 is considerably lower than that cited by Rondot for 1847 c. 2000,
                  he thus must have visited some time after Rondot.</note>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>John Edkins </cell>
              <cell>between <hi rend="bold">1848-1857</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Ferdinand von Richthofen </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1868</hi>-11-25/26
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>John Thomson </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1870 </hi>or <hi rend="bold">1871</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Jules Arène </cell>
              <cell>10 days in <hi rend="bold">1872</hi>-07 </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Archibald Little </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1875</hi>-09-27/28
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Julia Hughes summer </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1879</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Hampten C. DuBose </cell>
              <cell>between<hi rend="bold"> 1875-1886</hi>
                <hi rend="bold">
                  <note xml:id="ftn13" place="foot" n="13">DuBose 1886: 275 mentions the
                    steamer line that started service in c.1875, his visit must have taken
                    place after that date.</note>
                </hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Bernhard Laufer </cell>
              <cell>
                <hi rend="bold">1901</hi>
              </cell>
            </row>
          </table>
          <p>The people on this list, which could be extended well into the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, visited Putuo mainly because of its scenic qualities and
            its bathing beaches. As several sources (Nevius, Arène, Edkins) attest, already
            in the mid-19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century the island had become a popular
            bathing resort for the foreign community in Shanghai and Zhejiang. This fame
            lasted into the early decades of the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century when the
            third edition of Crow’s <hi rend="italic">Traveller’s Handbook to China</hi>
            says of Mount Putuo: “Among foreigners living in Shanghai it is known as the
            nearest bathing beach, to Chinese Buddhists it is the most sacred place in East
            China.”<note xml:id="ftn14" place="foot" n="14">Crow (1921:
              128-129).</note>
          </p>
          <p>Mount Putuo owed its prominence among foreigners in large part to its central
            location along China’s coast. It was accessible for the foreign communities that
            sprang up along the coast in the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, especially
            from the treaty ports of Shanghai and Ningbo. Travel into the interior of China
            was difficult for both missionaries and traders during the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, because of legal restrictions, rebellions and civil war.
            Ocean travel along the coast, on the other hand, was comparatively easy. Among
            expatriates in late 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and early 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
            century China, Mount Putuo was among the best known Buddhist sites. Not
            coincidentally therefore, Mount Putuo was discussed in great detail in two early
            20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century publications that introduced the site to a
            foreign readership.<note xml:id="ftn15" place="foot" n="15">Boerschmann (1911)
              is a dedicated study of the island and its architecture, while Johnston
              (1913: 259-312) has devoted a long chapter.</note>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">

          <head>Foreigners on Mount Putuo</head>
          <p>It was not love on first sight, however. The first two visitors, Gützlaff and
            Medhurst, who left a description of Mount Putuo were Protestant missionaries.
            While acknowledging the picturesque landscape, they felt entitled to express
            their disgust about the religious character of the island.<note xml:id="ftn16" place="foot" n="16">In the same vain, though somewhat less rabid, Culbertson
              (1857), who when observing a Buddhist ritual was reminded of “the mummeries
              practiced in the Roman Catholic Church” (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>. 101).
              For an apologetic comment about this generation of missionaries by a later
              colleague see Johnston (1913: 261f).</note> Gützlaff does not mince his
            words: </p>
          <p>A temple built on a projecting rock, beneath which the foaming sea dashed, gave
            us some idea of the genius of its inhabitants, in thus selecting the most
            attractive spot to celebrate the orgies of idolatry. … Though we were in a dark
            hall, standing before the largest image of Budha [sic], there was nothing
            impressive; even our English sailors were disgusted with the scene. … No females
            are allowed to live on the island, nor are there any laymen suffered to reside
            here, unless they be in the service of the priests. To maintain this numerous
            train of idlers, lands on the opposite island have been allotted for their use,
            which they farm out; but as this is still inadequate, they go upon begging
            expeditions not only into surrounding provinces, but even as far as Siam.<note xml:id="ftn17" place="foot" n="17">Gutzlaff (1834: 438, 442-443).</note>
          </p>
          <p>Medhurst too was disgusted with the Buddhist presence on the island:</p>
          <p>All the aids that could be collected from nature and art, were there
            concentrated, to render the scene lovely and enchanting. But to the eye of the
            Christian philanthropist, it presented on melancholy picture of moral and
            spiritual death. Viewed by the light of revelation, and in the prospect of
            eternity, the whole island of Putuo, with its picturesque scenery, its hundreds
            temples, and its six thousand priests, exhibited to the mind nothing but a
            useless waste of property, a gross misemployment of time, and a pernicious
            fostering of error, tending to corrupt the surrounding population, and to draw
            off their minds from the worship of the true God, the adoration of the phantom
            Buddha... On all sides, we were gratified by perceiving marks of decay, in the
            temples and adjacent buildings; and earnestly hope, that future travellers will
            find these worse than useless structures level with the ground; and the lazy
            drones who inhabit them, scattered abroad, or employed in promoting the welfare
            and intelligence of their fellow countrymen.<note xml:id="ftn18" place="foot" n="18">Medhurst (1838: 483, 486).</note>
          </p>
          <p>Thus the first descriptions of Mount Putuo by Europeans are filled with the
            gentle spirit of Christian mission in the Far East. The reason why Gützlaff and
            Medhurst visited at all was in order to “distribute good books for their [the
            monks’] instruction and benefit” (Medhurst 1838: 487). Ambling across the
            island’s “lovely and enchanting” landscape the missionaries were the vanguard of
            colonial expansion that materialized a few years later when, in July 1840, the
            British invaded and occupied Zhoushan. Gützlaff, by then in British employ,
            served for a while as the civil magistrate on Zhoushan during the occupation of
            the island, only a few years after his first visit there as a missionary.<note xml:id="ftn19" place="foot" n="19">Lutz (2008: 103). For a detailed first
              hand account of the (second) capture of Dinghai in 1841 see (Bernhard &amp;
              Hall 1846: 238-251).</note>
          </p>
          <p>In spite of their colonialist attitude, our twisted sources yield useful
            information. That women, for instance, were forbidden to spend the night on
            Mount Putuo has often been repeated in Western sources about Putuo, but does not
            appear in gazetteers of the period. It was independently observed by Fortune in
            1844 (Fortune 1847: 184), Little in 1875 (Little 1910: 178), and DuBose in
            c.1880 (DuBose 1886: 277), thus the policy must have been in place for some
            decades. The <hi rend="italic">Imperial Gazetteer </hi>of 1855, an encyclopedia
            of the world’s geography as owned and desired by the British Empire, has an
            entry on Mount Putuo that draws on the accounts of Gützlaff and Medhurst. It
            says: </p>
          <p>It [Mt. Putuo] is almost literally covered with monasteries, pavilions, temples,
            and other buildings appropriated to religious uses; besides grottoes, and other
            monuments of superstition, in which at least 2000 idle priests chant the praises
            of their idols, and live in ignorance, idolatry, vice, and dirt. No females are
            allowed to reside on Putuo, nor any besides priests, unless in their
            employ.<note xml:id="ftn20" place="foot" n="20">Blackie (1855: sub voc.
              “Puto”). Rondot(1847: 182) too writes that beside the nearly 2000 monks only
              200 lay people were allowed to live on the island. This seems in great
              contrast certainly to the Republican period and today, but also to previous
              periods. The gazetteers do not mention or at least not extensively discuss
              that the island was reserved for monks.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Not all early travelers to Mount Putuo were Christian supremacists and the
            reports by the Scottish botanist R. Fortune and the economist N. Rondot, who was
            part of a French expedition, were less harsh in their judgment of religion on
            the island. Both provide a wealth of detail about the site including its
            religious practices. Rondot, for example, included what is perhaps the first
            extensive retelling of the Miaoshan legend in a Western language (Rondot 1847:
            164-171) as well as descriptions of monastic garb and ritual (<hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>: 161-162).</p>
          <p>Fortune was informed, that the resident priests were fond of collecting plants, particularly
            Orchidacese, and that their collections were much increased by the itinerant
            habits of the begging priests, who visit the most distant provinces of the
            empire, as well as by the donations of the lay devotees, who come to Putuo at
            stated seasons of the year, to worship and leave their offerings in the
            temples.<note xml:id="ftn21" place="foot" n="21">Fortune (1847:
              181).</note>
          </p>
          <p>The Catholic priest Évariste Huc, a member of the Vincentian order, was much
            milder in his assessment of Buddhism on Mount Putuo. Huc had, compared to the
            Ningbo missionaries, traveled far and wide in China, Tibet and Mongolia. He too
            considered Chinese Buddhism in decline, especially when he compared it to
            Tibetan Buddhism that he had encountered in Tibet and Mongolia. Nevertheless, as
            his account of Mount Putuo shows, he sought contact with monks and appreciated
            their politeness.<note xml:id="ftn22" place="foot" n="22">Huc (1862[1854]:
              Vol.2, p. 232-236). On É. Huc see Simon Leys’ essay “Les tribulations d'un
              Gascon en Chine” (Leys 1999: 596-629).</note>
          </p>
          <p>After the Opium War resulted in the establishment of the first treaty ports, a
            growing number of missionaries descended on Ningbo. Until 1851, 15 Protestant
            missionaries of different denominations had settled in Ningbo, many bringing
            their families with them.<note xml:id="ftn23" place="foot" n="23">The Chinese
              RepositoryVol. 20 (1851): 530.</note> Among then were John L. and Helen S.
            C. Nevius, American Presbyterian missionaries that stayed in China for almost 40
            years (1854-1893). Their first years were spend in Ningbo, from where they
            visited Mount Putuo. John Nevius spent his first summer there in company of a
            friend 1854. An excerpt from his diary:</p>
          <p>Island of Putuo, Zhoushan Archipelago, sixty miles from Ningbo, August 16, 1854:
            Last week Mr. Cobbold, of the Church Missionary Society, having determined to
            take a trip to Putuo. on account of his health, kindly invited me to accompany
            him. As I have been closely confined to my work and needed a little change, I
            accepted his invitation, and soon found myself very much in the spirit of going.
            . . . We started with the tide at 7 p.m., and arrived at the mouth of the river
            about ten and anchored for the night. As the tide was just changing, Mr. Cobbold
            and I enjoyed a fine swim before going to bed. Yesterday at ten in the forenoon
            we reached the island of Zhoushan. . . . This morning, after all sorts of
            detentions from wind and tide and incompetent boatmen, we arrived at Putuo and
            anchored some distance from shore. There was, fortunately, a small boat close
            by, which took us off. We started at once for a walk up the hill behind the
            nearest temple, and on to the northern side of the island, enjoying many
            beautiful views from the summits of the hill. We visited the immense boulder
            which rests on a very slight foundation, scarcely bigger than a thimble.<note xml:id="ftn24" place="foot" n="24">Probably the <placeName>Pantuo Stone 盤陀石</placeName>, a famous site on
              the island. But perhaps the boulder seen in the background of the sketch
              drawn by Helen Nevius on the first photo of Putuo by John Thomson,
              below.</note> Several of the priests from an adjoining monastery following
            us, Mr. Cobbold had an opportunity of speaking to them of the folly of idolatry.
            They assented to all he said, but no doubt it seemed foolishness to them. The
            sun broke through the mist and we hastened back. I took shelter in a monastery,
            and Mr. Cobbold went to our boat He soon returned, bringing some food for our
            lunch, and also books and writing-materials. Having no bed or lounge, I was glad
            to lie down upon two tables furnished me by a priest, to get a little rest.
            After occupying them an hour or so, I left them to write, and I presume Mr.
            Cobbold has now appropriated them.</p>
          <p>Thursday: After breakfast this morning we followed the beach to the right until
            we passed the first monastery, and from there on to another near a very deep
            cave. . . . From there we went to ‘Tunbridge Wells,’ where there is another
            natural cave, and rocks piled up in a very fantastic manner. We found in the
            adjoining monastery a man from Shanghai who has taken temporary vows upon
            himself. He was very talkative, and somewhat intelligent. There was also a
            good-natured old priest, who had nothing to say, but assented to everything that
            was said to him. And there was another, a stupefied, besotted fellow, who sat in
            a little nook conning an old book, looking up and grinning at us occasionally. I
            procured a string of beads — a rosary — from the talkative Shanghai man, and the
            good-humored priest presented me with another. . . . When we reached the top of
            Veh-ting-san [<placeName>Fodingshan 佛頂山</placeName>] we found ourselves in the clouds,
            which were driving over the top, and the air was very cold. As we were thinly
            dad, and warm with climbing, we quickly started back. We got to our boat at
            seven o'clock, and the boatman at once shoved off and we started for Zhoushan,
            which place we reached about midnight ... I have been out of sorts ever since
            leaving home; still I have enjoyed the trip and hope to visit Putuo again.<note xml:id="ftn25" place="foot" n="25">Nevius (1895: 133-134). Omissions and
              abridgments in the original.</note>
          </p>
          <p>His wish was fulfilled when in the following two summers he visited Putuo again,
            this time with Helen, his newly betrothed wife. To Helen we owe the first
            account of Mount Putuo by a woman:</p>
          <p>Putuo is devoted exclusively to the Buddhists; having four large temples with
            monasteries attached, and not far from a hundred smaller ones. The number of
            priests is variously estimated from seven or eight hundred, to several
            thousands. I believe it is more than eight hundred years since this island was
            first devoted to religious purposes; and some of the buildings were constructed
            at that time. Others again are of much more recent date, but all, even the
            newest, have a dilapidated, faded appearance, which indicates a great falling
            off in resources, as well as in the devotion of the people generally to the
            Buddhist religion.... Adjoining this is a lotus pond, which, though not what it
            once was, is still very pretty. It is crossed by an arched stone bridge. There
            are numerous other buildings, — some used as temples for the idols, and some as
            sleeping places for the lazy, stupid priests, who doze away their lives in this
            pretty retreat. Had they a spark of energy or ambition, they would make some
            effort to rescue these buildings from the decay and ruin in which we now find
            them.... Our rooms were not in the Sien-z [前寺], but at the Heo-z [後寺],<note xml:id="ftn26" place="foot" n="26">The Qian si 前寺is the <placeName>Puji Temple 普濟寺</placeName>. The Hou si 後寺 (“Back
              Temple”) is the <placeName>Fayu Temple 法雨寺</placeName>.</note> about a mile further
            on. ... On three sides of our large room were windows, looking towards the sea,
            the Sien-z, and the Heo-z, of the latter of which our building formed part. ....
            One reason for our coming to the Heo-z, rather than either of the other temples
            nearer the landing, was its proximity to a sandy beach which was a capital
            bathing-place.<note xml:id="ftn27" place="foot" n="27">This is the beach
              today called <placeName>Qianbusha 千步沙</placeName>.</note> Some years before
            this, an English chaplain had lost his life while bathing on this beach; having
            ventured, I suppose, to an unsafe distance. Thus on our guard against possible
            danger, we had many refreshing baths. As several other families from Ningbo were
            also at Putuo, we planned some delightful picnics and rambles in company to
            various points of interest. During the summer, years ago, it was very customary
            for foreigners from Ningbo and Shanghai to visit this island; but of late such
            visits seem nearly discontinued. Since the opening of Japan, and of other parts
            of China, by the recent treaties, foreigners, in choosing summer resorts, have
            generally given the preference to places situated in more northern latitudes, or
            more accessible.<note xml:id="ftn28" place="foot" n="28">Nevius (1869: 45-48).
            </note>
          </p>
          <p>The <hi rend="italic">Sien-z</hi> (=<hi rend="italic">Qiansi</hi>)<hi rend="italic"> </hi> or “Front Temple,” today the <placeName>Puji Temple 普濟寺</placeName>, was the older of the two main
            temples of Mount Putuo. Helen’s memoirs <hi rend="italic">Our Life in China
            </hi> includes a sketch she must have drawn at one of her visits 1855-56:</p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <graphic url="Pictures/100000000000022E0000034FC41D6CA328075E7D.png" />
              <head>Figure 1: Helen Nevius 1869: Page facing p. 46. Public Domain.</head>
            </figure>
            <figure>
              <graphic url="Pictures/1000000000000640000004E1F0E3E02C33807B61.jpg" />
              <head>Figure 2: John Thomson 1874: Vol. 3, Plate VII-15. Scanned image from the original plates: CC License (Wellcome Trust)</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>A photo of the lake before the Puji Temple was taken from the spot some 15 years
            later by John Thomson, one of the first photographers who traveled to China, and
            must have visited Mount Putuo 1870 or 1871. This might be the earliest photo of
            Mount Putuo.<note xml:id="ftn29" place="foot" n="29">A perhaps earlier series of
              photos of Mount Putuo and Zhoushan were in the collection of Robert Wilson
              Shufeldt (1822-1895), who was in the archipelago 1866 or 1867. These are now
              kept at the United States National Anthropological Archives (Inventory Nos:
              04513300-04537900). Thomson seems only have taken the photo above of Mount
              Putuo. It should be noted that next to the well-known series of ca. 200
              photos published in Thomson (1874), which were later republished and
              included in other publications, there are still more unpublished images. The
              Wellcome Library owns a collection of Thomson’s original glass plate
              negatives and has digitized 662 of these and made them available as a
              digital collection. Another photo of the temple taken from the same spot a
              few years later is found in the Edward Bang Drew collection in the
              Harvard-Yenching Library (Identifier: Hv37-29).</note>
          </p>
          <p>In the text accompanying the image Thomson speaks of a large community of c. 2000
            monastics, which he describes unfavorably as “...lusty, lazy monks, the pious
            paupers who spend their years in drowsily chanting to Buddha, and who, if dirt
            and sloth will foster the growth of piety, must indeed be accounted hold
            men.”<note xml:id="ftn30" place="foot" n="30">Thomson 1874: Vol.3, facing
              Plate VII-15.</note> He also remarks on the economy of the site: “The
            revenues for the support of these various religious establishments are derived
            from three sources: the rent of church lands, the contributions of pilgrims and
            the labours of the mendicant priests.”<note xml:id="ftn31" place="foot" n="31">Ibid.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Among those labors was presumably to rent out rooms to foreign guests, foreign
            women being exempted from the prohibition against women pilgrims staying
            over-night. An account by Julia Hughes, the wife of an officer in the British
            Imperial Maritime Customs Service, who visited in summer 1879, describes the
            very effective catering service arranged in a Buddhist monastery, complete with
            meat and champagne.<note xml:id="ftn32" place="foot" n="32">Hughes (1881:
              258-259). To Hughes we also owe an account of how in the 1870s a lady bathed
              on the beaches of Mount Putuo: “After visiting one or two other temples, we
              strolled down to a lovely beach, in a secluded corner of which our kind
              captain had erected a tent for my own special comfort, I being the only lady
              of the party, and having attired myself in a bathing costume, I indulged in
              a most refreshing sea-bath. When I was again dressed it was getting late,
              and having joined the others, who had been bathing in another part of the
              beach, we all proceeded towards the landing-place.” (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi>, 262-263).</note>
          </p>
          <p>A close friend of the Nevius’ was William Martin who, like them, stayed in China
            for more than forty years. His memoirs confirm again that the Ningbo
            missionaries visited Mount Putuo regularly during the hot summers.</p>
          <p>Beyond Zhoushan, to the east, and parted from it by a narrow channel, lies the
            sacred isle of Puto. Like lona in early times, and Mount Athos at the present
            day, it is exclusively an abode of monks, no native woman being allowed to live
            there on any pretext. This rule, however, is not enforced in the case of
            foreigners; and, taking our wives and children with us, we sometimes sought
            refuge there from the heat of Ningbo.… In the daytime we climbed the hills or
            bathed in the surf, and in the evening inhaled the ocean breeze while we viewed
            the phosphorescent waves breaking on the shore in long billows of flame.<note xml:id="ftn33" place="foot" n="33">Martin 1897: 119-120.</note>
          </p>
          <p>The visits to “the most lovely spot in Far Cathay” (DuBose 1886: 274), however,
            were not altogether carefree. Apart from the dangers of the surf, the Chinese
            defeat in the Opium Wars had weakened government control of the Zhoushan
            archipelago and, as always during such periods of weakness, this allowed the
            rise of piracy. Between the 1840s and the 1870s the waters around Zhoushan were
            not entirely safe for travel, as Martin and one of his colleagues, W. A.
            Russell, found out when they tried to join their families on Mount Putuo. </p>
          <p>Going on deck, as we approached a narrow channel we saw many lights dancing over
            the surface of the water, and heard an occasional discharge of small arms. In a
            solitary place this looked suspicious; and the next moment we perceived through
            the twilight the outline of seven large Canton junks lying at anchor. We pursued
            our course, hoping to pass them unobserved, but when we were just abreast of the
            fleet, a boat was lowered from the side of one of the junks and gave chase. The
            wind had fallen, and we were soon overtaken. Springing on board, the pirates
            began beating our sailors to compel them to slacken sail. Turning to us, they
            said, <hi rend="italic">Pu pa pu pa</hi> (“You have nothing to fear”). Our boat
            was lashed to the side of a large junk, and the free-booters made free with our
            fresh provisions — the only booty they found in our possession. The pirates were
            evidently disappointed. “Who are you,” they asked, “that you have no goods? As
            you have no opium, you are not merchants; and as you have no firearms, you are
            not soldiers; who and what are you?” “We are missionaries,” we quietly replied.
            “Missionaries!” exclaimed a handsome young man, whom we recognized as the leader
            of the prize crew. “You preach about Jesus — you are good men; we will not hurt
            you.” He then told us that he had been in a mission chapel at Whampo, near
            Canton, and there heard missionaries preach the gospel. Becoming communicative,
            he added that he and his party, thrown out of business by the outbreak of
            rebellion [i.e. the Taiping], had been forced to take to the sea. “It was a bad
            business,” he knew, “but there was no help for it.” In searching our persons for
            money, of which they found very little, they had stripped off my coat and taken
            away Russell's shoes and watch. My own watch, or rather my wife's, I had taken
            off and left at home, not wishing to risk the loss of an object which she held
            precious. Observing me in my shirt-sleeves, the young leader pointed to Russell
            and asked if we were not “all the same”? “Oh yes,” said I; “but one of your
            fokees (“pals”) has carried my coat away.” The young man left us and in a moment
            came back with the coat. The shoes, too, were restored, but not the watch;
            which, however, was brought to the owner for an explanation of the mode of
            winding and setting.<note xml:id="ftn34" place="foot" n="34">Martin (1897:
              122-123).</note>
          </p>
          <p>While the Ningbo missionaries enjoyed Mount Putuo for its scenic beauty, other
            travelers were looking for different assets. An interested visitor was Ferdinand
            von Richthofen whose descriptions of the island in <hi rend="italic">China -
              Ergebnisse eigener Reisen und darauf gegründeter Studien </hi>(1877-1912)
            are mainly geological, with the exception of a comment on the <placeName>Huiji Temple</placeName>: </p>
          <p>[At the Huiji Temple:] Here lived 23 monks in poverty and simplicity. They were
            just holding a procession with sombre chanting and incense-burning. Refectory
            and cells showed how little they desired. The monks were said to own an old
            library and have a reputation for clerical erudition.<note xml:id="ftn35" place="foot" n="35">Richthofen (1855-1912: Vol.3, p. 656).</note>
          </p>
          <p>It is only in his posthumously published diaries that we find a more detailed
            account of his visit to the island. It contains an interesting remark about how
            the fortune telling, so common to Chinese temple culture, on Mount Putuo was
            geared towards fishermen:</p>
          <p>
            <hi rend="color(#000000)">From the place where we anchored we came first to a
              small temple, where the Europeans tend to stay. In the main temple we found
              some priests, one of their best sources of income is fortune telling. In a
              box there are some hundred lots. One draws a lot and a priest who sits in a
              stall, exchanges, for a small fee, the number for a printed piece of paper.
              We made the experiment and received some commonplace divinations which were
              mainly concerned with fishing. This is because the place is visited
              especially by fishermen who pray here and seem to consider the place as some
              sort of oracle. I was prophesied a lucky catch in a river. An other source
              of income is the sale of images of the temple deity, a map of the temples
              and their surroundings, a sort of rosary etc.</hi>
            <hi rend="color(#000000)">
              <note xml:id="ftn36" place="foot" n="36">Richthofen (1907: 47). For
                another account of fortune telling at Mount Putuo see Hughes (1881:
                262).</note>
            </hi>
            <hi rend="color(#000000)"> </hi>
          </p>
          <p>The maps mentioned by von Richhofen here (and earlier by Rondot (1847: 161))
            would have been the kind of simple woodblock prints for the use of pilgrims of
            which some specimens have survived in libraries and museums.<note xml:id="ftn37" place="foot" n="37">See e.g. the maps in the American Museum of Natural
              History (ASIA/ 0578, No. 70/11655).</note> Von Richthofen’s survey of
            China’s geography and geology was done not merely for scientific purposes. His
            diary notes reveal other motives as well: </p>
          <p>
            <hi rend="color(#000000)">As free port in the hands of a power such as Prussia
              Zhoushan would gain a paramount position. The harbor can be fortified easily
              and the navy flotilla would control the traffic with northern China and
              Japan. It would turn into an important center of commerce. Ningbo would
              wither away and Shanghai be greatly diminished, because property would be
              much safer here.[...] For the Chinese the islands are but of little value,
              and a purchase could perhaps be arranged for a not too high price.</hi>
            <hi rend="color(#000000)">
              <note xml:id="ftn38" place="foot" n="38">Richthofen
                (1907: 44).</note>
            </hi>
          </p>
          <p>The practical-minded von Richthofen also included a number of maps of the
            Zhoushan archipelago including one of Mount Putuo:<note xml:id="ftn39" place="foot" n="39">For Chinese maps and representations of Mount Putuo see
              Bingenheimer (2016: Ch.2).</note>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <graphic url="Pictures/1000000000000348000002F896B00E60AF071A96.png" />
              <head>Map1: Richthofen 1877-1912: Vol. 3, p. 655</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
          <p>
            <figure>
              <graphic url="Pictures/10000000000009CB00000C622AFA1D0FF040449A.jpg" />
              <head>Map 2: Modern Map of Putuo, with places mentioned in the text. Note the
                artificial land that was created in the western bay of the island in the late
                20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century.</head>
            </figure>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div type="section">

          <head>Conclusion</head>
          <p>The travel records of foreigners, whether created with missionary, imperialist or
            simply touristic intent, contain information about Mount Putuo, at least some of
            which is not found in the local gazetteers.The gazetteers, of course, suffer
            from their own – literati – bias and have disregarded many aspects that Western
            visitors found remarkable. They do not seem to mention, for instance, the
            prohibition against women residing on the island which is mentioned by almost
            all foreign witnesses. This prohibition seems to have been in force at least for
            several decades during the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century, and was probably
            limited to pilgrims not the resident population of fishing folk. It is hard to
            imagine, however, that all women pilgrims were confined to one day visits and
            returned to adjacent Zhoushan by nightfall. This might be one of those
            prohibitions that were widely announced, but not too rigorously enforced.<note xml:id="ftn40" place="foot" n="40">For more prohibitions concerning women
              and temples in China see Goossaert (2008).</note> Another facet not usually
            emphasized by the gazetteers is that fishing communities were an important group
            of devotees for the religious establishments on Mount Putuo. This is mentioned
            by the eye-witness reports of their worship by Gutzlaff (1834: 443), Rondot
            (1847: 158), and von Richthofen (1907: 47). </p>
          <p>Also not mentioned in the gazetteers as far as I see are the Tibetan inscriptions
            on the island mentioned by Laufer (1909: 568) and Kupfer (1911: 62). These
            inscriptions, almost certainly the mantra <hi rend="italic">oṃ maṇi padme
              huṃ</hi>, have vanished in the 20<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century. That Mount
            Putuo was also visited by at least some Tibetan and Mongol Buddhists during the
            Qing is not in itself surprising, considering the strong Tibetan Buddhist
            presence in the north, in Beijing and at Mount Putuo. Nevertheless past
            gazetteers and the site today do not reference Tibetan Buddhism in any way –
            textually, epigraphically, or architecturally.</p>
          <p>Perhaps the most important information provided by foreign accounts pertains to
            the number of monks in residence. Disregarding the exaggerated figure of 6000
            that is cited by Medhurst (1838: 483), most early travelers report c. 2000 monks
            (Gutzlaff 1834: 443, Fortune 1847: 185, Rondot 1847: 182). Against that
            estimates from after the Taiping wars, speak of about 1000 monks (Butler 1879:
            122, DuBose 1886: 277, Boerschman 1911: 12, Johnston 1913: 316).<note xml:id="ftn41" place="foot" n="41">Thomson who stayed only shortly around
              1870/71, but in his description also mentions 2000 monks, he might have been
              quoting from older sources. A Chinese traveler visiting in 1913 corroborates
              the lower figure of “somewhat more than 1000” (Gao 2015: 139).</note> If
            Culbertson is correct and the number of monks had fallen to 300 in 1857<note xml:id="ftn42" place="foot" n="42">“The number of priests, once perhaps
              reaching three thousand, now hardly reaches three hundred.” (Culbertson
              1857: 97).</note> the decline must have happened after Rondot’s visit in
            1847.</p>
          <p>Although these numbers are estimates, the discrepancy between the size of the
            monastic population before and after the Taiping, combined with Culbertson’s
            observation, indicates a drop in the monastic population in the 1850s. The main
            reason for the decline was probably the Taiping civil war (1850-1864), which
            directly or indirectly affected the movement of supplies and people all through
            central China and the lower Yangzi region. Qing naval forces, already expelled
            from Zhoushan during the British occupation, would have been ordered inland to
            fight the Taiping. Pirates – Martin’s “free-booters” – filled the power vacuum
            in the archipelago after the British left for Hong Kong, which they had
            exchanged for Zhoushan. The pirates interrupted pilgrimage traffic and thus
            affected the economy of the island. Consequently, as mentioned above, the
            gazetteers of Mount Putuo show a lack of information for the 19<hi rend="sup">th</hi> century regarding the succession of abbots, miracle tales, and
            other matters for the decades around 1850. All this indicates that the Taiping
            civil war and to a lesser degree the short-lived British occupation of
            Zhoushan’s main harbor interrupted pilgrimage travel to Mount Putuo in the
            mid-19th century.</p>
          <p>The downturn was temporary. Whereas in the 1840s Abbé Huc found “the vast
            monasteries of Putuo, where once large numbers of monks congregated, now almost
            entirely abandoned to legions of rats and huge spiders,” visitors in the late
            1870s saw a rejuvenated pilgrimage site. In a lecture delivered before the
            Ningpo Book Club on January 29, 1879 John Butler, another Ningbo missionary,
            gave an account of “Modern Putuo”:</p>
          <p>Modern Putuo begins with the era of rebuilding, on a large and permanent scale,
            and this era has commenced within the last ten years. While the fear of pirates
            hovered around the island, the priests were chary to bring forward their buried
            wealth and Buddhism appeared as dead. Now that merchant steamers are daily
            passing back and forth in sight of its shores, and gunboats, native and foreign
            make frequent visits to its waters, the fears of the priests have been quieted,
            and there is a simultaneous movement all over the island, to repair the old
            temples and to build new ones.<note xml:id="ftn43" place="foot" n="43">Butler
              (1879: 120).</note>
          </p>
          <p>Later Butler again remarks on the role of steamships in the development of
            shipping routes to Putuo:</p>
          <p>I have been so struck with this appearance of revival and activity that I have
            enquired of some of the oldest priests on the island, the cause, and all give
            the same reasons, viz., a sense of security that their buildings will not be
            burned nor their contents rifled, and this security and immunity from danger, is
            the result of foreign commerce and civilization, in driving pirates from the
            seas, and introducing the era of steam into Chinese waters.<note xml:id="ftn44" place="foot" n="44">Ibid.</note>
          </p>
          <p>Thus it seems to Butler that Buddhism on Mount Putuo, which appeared to its
            Western visitors to have fallen on hard times all by itself, was now rescued by
            the arrival of “foreign commerce and civilization.” A truly amazing conclusion,
            and in its lack of reflection, contrition, and shame in line with Western
            attitudes for a century and more to come.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <listBibl>
        <bibl>Arène, Jules. 1875. “Excursion de Deux Baigneurs Européens a l’Ile Sacrée de
          Poutou.” <hi rend="italic">L’Explorateur</hi> Vol. 20.1 (1875): 467-471.</bibl>
        <bibl>Bernhard, W.D.; Hall, W.H. 1846. <hi rend="italic">The Nemesis in China -
            comprising a history of the late war in that country</hi>. London: Henry
          Colburn. (3rd Edition)</bibl>
        <bibl>Baycroft, Anne. 2017. “Gendered Readings of Ritual: Exploring Narratives of
          Chinese Religion through Nineteenth Century Christian Missionary Writings.”
          Unpublished MA thesis (University of Saskatchewan).</bibl>
        <bibl>Bingenheimer, Marcus. 2016. <hi rend="italic">Island of Guanyin – Mount Putuo and
            Its Gazetteers</hi>. New York &amp; London: Oxford University Press.</bibl>
        <bibl>Blackie, Walker Graham. 1855-56. <hi rend="italic">The Imperial Gazetteer - A
            General dictionary of Geography, physical, political, statistical and
            descriptive.</hi> 4 Vols. Glasgow: Blackie and Son.</bibl>
        <bibl>Boerschmann, Ernst. 1911. <hi rend="italic">P’u T’o Shan – Die Heilige
            Ins</hi>
          <hi rend="italic">el der Kuan-Yin der Göttin der
            Barmherzigkeit.</hi> Berlin: Georg Reimer.
        </bibl>
        <bibl>Butler, John. 1879. “Pootoo Ancient and Modern— A Lecture Delivered before the
          Ningbo Book Club, January, 29, 1879.” <hi rend="italic">Chinese Recorder and
            Missionary Journal</hi> Vol. 10: 108–124.</bibl>
        <bibl>Crow, Carl. 1921. <hi rend="italic">The Travelers ’ Handbook for China (Including
            Hongkong)</hi>. 3rd ed.</bibl>
        <bibl>New York: Dodd, Mead and Co.</bibl>
        <bibl>Culbertson, Michael Simpson (1819-1862). 1857. <hi rend="italic">Darkness in the
            flowery land - Religious Notions and Popular Superstitions in North
            China</hi>. New York: Scribner.</bibl>
        <bibl>DuBose, Hampden C. 1886. <hi rend="italic">The Dragon, Image, and Demon: Or, The
            Three Religions of China</hi>. London: Partridge &amp; Co.</bibl>
        <bibl>Eggert, Marion. 2004. <hi rend="italic">Vom Sinn des Reisens. Chinesische
            Reiseschriften vom 16. bis zum frühen 19. Jahrhundert.</hi> Wiesbaden:
          Harrassowitz.</bibl>
        <bibl>Gao, Henian 高鶴年. 2015. <hi rend="italic">Wuzinian gaidingben Mingshan youfang ji
          </hi>戊子年改訂本 名山遊訪記. Hongkong: Xinyitang 心一堂. Edited by Chen Yingning 陳攖寧 and Pu
          Tuanzi 蒲團子.</bibl>
        <bibl>Goossaert, Vincent. 2008. “Irrepressible Female Piety: Late Imperial Bans on
          Women Visiting Temples.” <hi rend="italic">Nan Nü</hi> 10 (2008), 212-241.</bibl>
        <bibl>Gutzlaff, Charles [=Gützlaff, Karl F. A.]. 1834. <hi rend="italic">Journal of
            three voyages along the coast of China, in 1831, 1832, &amp; 1833, with
            notices of Siam, Corea, and the Loo-Choo islands.</hi> London: Frederick
          Westley and A.H. Davis. Preface by William Ellis.</bibl>
        <bibl>Edkins, John (?). 1857. “The Monasteries at Mount Putuo” <hi rend="italic">North-China Herald</hi> March 7th 1857, p.127. (signed J E).</bibl>
        <bibl>Eggert, Marion. 2004. “Der Reisebericht (youji).” In: Marion Eggert, Wolfgang
          Kubin, Rolf Trauzettel, Thomas Zimmer. <hi rend="italic">Die klassische
            chinesische Prosa Essay, Reisebericht, Skizze, Brief - Vom Mittelalter bis
            zur Neuzeit.</hi> München: K. G. Saur Verlag, pp 117–202. (Geschichte
          derChinesischen Literatur Vol. 4)</bibl>
        <bibl>Fortune, Robert. 1847. <hi rend="italic">Three Years’ Wanderings in the Northern
            Provinces of China, including a Visit to the Tea, Silk and Cotton
            Countries.</hi> London: John Murray.</bibl>
        <bibl>Huc, Évariste Régis. 1862 [1854]. <hi rend="italic">L’Empire Chinois.</hi> 2
          Vols. Paris: Gaume &amp; Duprey.</bibl>
        <bibl>Hughes, Julia (Mrs. Thomas Francis). 1881. <hi rend="italic">Among the Sons of
            Han: Notes of a Six Years' Residence in Various Parts of China and Formosa.
          </hi>London: Tinsley Brothers.</bibl>
        <bibl>Johnston, Reginald F. 1913 <hi rend="italic">Buddhist China</hi>. London: Murray,
          1913.</bibl>
        <bibl>Kupfer, Carl F. 1904. “Pootoo – China’s Sacred Island” <hi rend="italic">The East
            of Asia Magazine</hi> Vol. 3 (1904): 264-281. </bibl>
        <bibl>Kupfer, Carl F. 1911. <hi rend="italic">Sacred Places in China</hi>. Cincinnati:
          The Western Methodist Book Concern.</bibl>
        <bibl>Laufer, Bernhard. 1909 [1976]. “Die Kanjur Ausgabe des Kaisers K’ang-hsi.” <hi rend="italic">Izvestija Imperatorskoj Akademii nauk</hi> 1909: 567-574.
          Reprint in: Laufer, Berthold: <hi rend="italic">Kleinere Schriften.</hi>
          Wiesbaden 1976, Vol.1: 1352-1359.</bibl>
        <bibl>Leys, Simon. 1999. <hi rend="italic">Essais sur la Chine.</hi> Paris: Robert
          Laffont. (“Les tribulations d'un Gascon en Chine” was first published in <hi rend="italic">Le forêt en feu</hi>, 1983<hi rend="italic">.</hi>)</bibl>
        <bibl>Little, Archibald. 1910. <hi rend="italic">Gleanings from fifty years in China.
          </hi>London: Low, Marston and Co.</bibl>
        <bibl>Lutz, Jessie Gregory. 2008. <hi rend="italic">Opening China: Karl F. A. Gützlaff
            and Sino-Western relations, 1827-1852.</hi> Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdmans.</bibl>
        <bibl>Martin, William Alexander Parsons. 1897. <hi rend="italic">A Cycle of Cathay, or,
            China, South and North.</hi> New York: Revell.</bibl>
        <bibl>Medhurst, Walter H. 1938.<hi rend="italic"> China: its state and prospects with
            especial Reference to the Spread of the Gospel.</hi> London: John Snow.
          Illustrations by G. Baxter.</bibl>
        <bibl>Meyer-Fong, Toby. 2013. <hi rend="italic">What Remains-Coming to Terms with Civil
            War in 19th </hi>
        </bibl>
        <bibl>
          <hi rend="italic">Century China</hi>. Stanford, CA: Stanford University
          Press.
        </bibl>
        <bibl>Nevius, Helen S. C. 1869. <hi rend="italic">Our Life in China.</hi> New York: R.
          Carter and Brothers.</bibl>
        <bibl>Nevius, Helen S. C. 1895. <hi rend="italic">The Life of John Livingstone
            Nevius.</hi> New York: Fleming.</bibl>
        <bibl>
          <anchor type="bookmark-start" xml:id="id___DdeLink__3596_3312230221" />Richthofen,
          Ferdinand von. 1877-1912
          <ptr type="bookmark-end" target="#id___DdeLink__3596_3312230221" />.
          <anchor type="bookmark-start" xml:id="id___DdeLink__2475_942533919" />
          <hi rend="italic">China - Ergebnisse
            eigener Reisen und darauf gegründeter Studien</hi>
          <ptr type="bookmark-end" target="#id___DdeLink__2475_942533919" />
          <hi rend="italic">.</hi> 5 vols.
          Berlin: D. Reimer.
        </bibl>
        <bibl>Richthofen, Ferdinand von. 1907. <hi rend="italic">Tagebücher ans China.</hi> 2
          Vols. Berlin: D. Reimer.</bibl>
        <bibl>Rondot, Natalis. 1847. “Excursion à l’île de Pou-tou (province de tché-kiang) 7
          et 8 Octobre, 1845.” <hi rend="italic">Séances et travaux de l‘Académie de
            Reims</hi> Tome 5 (Mai 1846 – Aout 1846): 159-195.</bibl>
        <bibl>Thomson, John. 1874. <hi rend="italic">Illustrations of China and its people. A
            series of two hundred photographs, with letterpress descriptive of the
            places and people represented.</hi> Sampson Low: Marston, Low, and Searle. 4
          Vols.</bibl>
        <bibl>Wang, Liansheng 王连胜, 1999: Putuoluojiashan zhi 普陀洛迦山誌. Shanghai: Shanghai shudian
          上海書店.</bibl>
      </listBibl>
      <listPlace>
        <place>
          <placeName xml:lang="en">Putuo Shan</placeName>
          <placeName xml:lang="zh">普陀山</placeName>
          <idno>https://www.geonames.org/1898813/putuo-shan.html</idno>
        </place>
        <place>
          <placeName xml:lang="en">Puji Si</placeName>
          <placeName xml:lang="zh">普濟寺</placeName>
          <idno>https://www.geonames.org/1894725/puji-si.html</idno>
        </place>
      </listPlace>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
